Well, hello. Welcome back. You survived
week one, day one, and you're back for
week one, day two. Thank you. It's a
purple day. There's that purple stripe
in the middle there. And that means that
today is another theory day, our second
theory day. And I've got two bits of bad
news for you. One of them is that today
is going to be a lot about me talking. I
like these sessions to be mostly
practical stuff doing things and today's
going to be a bit of of like theory and
material, but I'll I'll try and get
through it quickly and it paves the way
for lots of practical stuff to come. And
the second bad thing is that today is
going to be perhaps somewhat it's going
to be foundational. It's going to be
some of the basics and some of you
probably already know this stuff in
which case please put me on 2x steam
through this. There'll still be some
interesting bits I'll put in there for
for everybody, but it is going to be
reasonably foundational. If you are new
to this, then listen up. There's some
important stuff to cover today. Let's
get into it. And I am just going to
start by level setting with the the sort
of basics like what what is an LLM? I
imagine everybody knows, but let's just
make sure we're on the on the same page.
So a large language model such as GPT of
course it is something which is designed
to predict what text what words should
come after an input. You give it an
input sequence of words and it says what
will come next. It's like autocomplete
on steroids. And of course we know that
the way it actually works is it's
basically this enormous pattern matching
statistical engine. It's been fed tons
and tons of training data, example data
from the internet and far beyond. And
it's looked at all of this data. It's
learned patterns in the data. And so,
it's got really good when it's given
some input text at predicting what will
come next. And of course, I used the
word words there, but it's really what
we call tokens. the input is actually a
sequence of tokens where a token is a
kind of chunk of a few letters that
often is a word but is often also a part
of a word. And so there's a sequence of
these input tokens and the output from
an LLM is not necessarily the the most
likely next token. We often say it that
way, but what it actually gives you is
the probability of every possible next
token. If the input is 2 + 2 is then the
output there's a very high probability
that the output is the token for four.
But there might also be a probability of
other words like the word bananas but
presumably that would be a very low
probability. 2 + 2 is bananas is not a
very common thing to say. It won't have
appeared very often in the training
data. But that's the idea. The input is
a sequence of these things called tokens
and the output is the probability of the
next token. That's what an LLM does. And
I imagine you're familiar with this. But
of course, one of the ways that LLMs
work is that they generate the output
one token at a time. So if the input is
something like what is the capital of
France, then the first word, the first
token that it predicts to come next
might be the word the. And then you'd
pass in what is the capital of France?
The And the next token might be capital.
And then what is the capital of France?
The capital. And then what is the
capital of France? The capital of France
is and then Paris. And so it generates
things one token at a time. And the
whole input is passed back in with all
the tokens so far. And then it predicts
the next token. And that is the way that
LLMs are run. That process is called
inference and they're run that way to
generate the output one token at a time.
And if you want to know more about that,
I have a sort of YouTube series that
goes through this, a playlist that I
will include in the course resources. I
imagine you know this already, but it's
good that we're on the same page. Okay,
that's an LLM. And then also so we're on
the same page, there is something
different but confusingly sounding
similar called an like an AI application
or an AI product. And this is something
that uses an LLM to achieve a business
goal, but it's got software written
around that call to an LLM. And the
distinction I'm trying to make here is
that something like there's a there's an
LLM that's very well known that's called
GPT that I'm sure you're familiar with.
GPT is an LLM. It's something which is a
model that predicts next tokens and then
there is an AI application that's called
chat GPT and that is a piece of software
that wraps around calling GPT and it has
other functionality. It has things like
a memory and the ability to search the
web and other stuff built around using
the GPT LLM and chat GPT then is a
classic example. The cursor agent that
we used yesterday is another example. If
you use Dualingo to learn a new
language, the Dualingo Max plan has a
premium feature that lets you chat with
an AI in order to learn a language.
That's another one. You may be familiar
with Atlassian Robo, which is like Genai
built into the Atlassian suite of
products. There's so many different
places where you will find Genai being
packaged into an application. And the
the reason that I draw attention to this
and and all of the many others is just
to draw that distinction between a
software product, an application that
uses an LLM from the LLM itself. Keep in
your mind separate chat GBT the product
from GPT the LLM which can be called to
generate the most likely next token to
follow a sequence. And that GPT LLM sits
behind the chat GPT product. And ever
since the release of Chat GPT in 2022,
we've all been a bit surprised that
autocomplete, basically predictive text
on steroids, is able to show this
apparent intelligence. It's able to do
things like we saw the cursor agent do,
and it's able to be like like chat GPT.
It's it's able to have an informed
conversation with us. It's it's very
very surprising. And there are a few
tricks that underly this. And in
particular, there are four tricks that I
want to highlight that are that are
written in software. They're sort of
built around this call to this thing
that just predicts likely next tokens.
And let me quickly go through four of
these tricks with you now. And the first
trick, which is one again I imagine most
of you are super clear on already, but
let's get on the same page. I call it
the illusion of memory. And it's
recognizing this very simple point which
is that every time that you use an LLM
like GPT from OpenAI, it is completely
stateless. GPT is a model, a data
science model that takes an input
sequence of tokens and it predicts what
will follow that input sequence and it's
completely stateless in that every time
you call it with an input sequence, it's
it's got no knowledge of previous calls.
Every call is a separate call. And so if
you write some code that just uses the
GPT model and you say, "I'm Ed." And it
replies, "Hi, Ed." And then you send
another call to the LLM, you you then
use the same LLM to put in a new input
sequence, which is, "Who am I?" It's
going to respond with something like, "I
don't know. I don't have that
information." That's the most likely
text to come after, "Who am I?" But
wait, you say that that doesn't match my
experience. I I use chat GPT and for
sure it keeps the conversation thread
going. If I say uh who am I? It will say
you're Ed. You just told me. Okay. Well,
you probably know this, but but that is
because of this trick, this sneaky
little trick, which is of course that
every time you call an LLM, you don't
just pass in something like who am I?
You pass in the complete conversation so
far. So what actually happens with chat
GPT when you're using the product chat
GPT is that you start by saying hi Ed
and it responds hello Ed and then the
next message that gets sent to GPT is
the whole conversation so far I'm Ed hi
Ed who am I the next thing I've typed
and when that entire input sequence is
sent in of course the LLM predicts the
most likely next token is something like
you're red you just told me you're at.
And that gives this illusion that chat
GPT has a memory. It is in fact just a
byproduct of every single time the LLM
is called, the entire conversation so
far is passed in. Most of you knew that
already. And if you didn't, you're like,
"Oh, I see." And if you do something
like my my uh AI engineering core track,
we actually make these calls and you see
it happening just in case you don't
believe me. And the second trick that
again people are pretty familiar with at
this point is this trick called
reasoning or thinking. And this began
out as this this thing we discovered
where when you were putting in this
input sequence to GPT if you put at the
end of the input sequence please think
step by step you tended to get better
outcomes which was sort of surprising
and that led over time to this different
way of working with LLMs in which they
were trained before they give you the
answer to output the way in which
they're going to come up with the
answer. And it's very strange, but it
turns out that as a side effect of
generating tokens to describe what it's
going to do, you end up getting better
outcomes. And that sounds it just sounds
hokey. It sounds too good to be true.
And yet it works. And here's a sort of
classic example. Again, I do this on my
AI engineering course. You could have
the question, hey, you toss two coins,
one of them is heads. What's the chances
the other one is tails? And I show that
when you run this with a model without
it outputting tokens to give its
reasoning, it will give an answer like a
half 50/50, which is what you might
instinctively think would be the right
answer. But in fact, it's one of those
annoying trick questions, which is a
clever little trick. Uh you could you
could ask chat GPT if you wanted to tell
you why, but the real answer is
twothirds. And if you ask it to explain
itself, if you if you want it to output
how it will think about this first and
then come up with the answer, then it
tends to get the answer right. It says
2/3 and it first says this is probably a
trick question. I should think this one
through and it realizes of course you're
in this situation where you're not
saying which one of the coins is heads
and that means that in twothirds of the
cases the other one will be tails. Look
it up. It's sneaky. But that is this
trick called reasoning or thinking. And
it's resulted in much stronger models
that are trained to generate tokens to
think through what they're going to do
before they do